Kaj Klitgaard Papers
Kaj Klitgaard Papers
1914-1966
Klitgaard, Kaj
0.5 linear ft.
Correspondence (1914-1966); photographs, sketchbooks, and published material, including articles and clippings. Correspondents include Egmont Arens, Peggy Bacon, Rockwell Kent, Alfred Kreymborg, Harry E. Maule, William McFee, Ogden Nash, John Crowe Ransom, Henry Morton Robinson, Franklin D. Roosevelt, Charles Allen Smart, and Lowell Thomas. Additional letters of many of the correspondents can be found in a scrapbook.
149107
Biographical History
Danish-American painter, novelist, author, seaman (1888-1953).
Scope and Contents of the Collection
Spanning the years 1914 through 1966, the Kaj Klitgaard Papers comprises biographical material, correspondence, artwork, writings, and memorabilia of the Danish-American author, painter, illustrator, educator, and master mariner (1888-1953). Though revealing little about his life in Denmark or his wartime experiences, the collection provides insight into Klitgaard's professional career and personal life in the United States, especially when used in conjunction with the Papers of his wife, Georgina Klitgaard, whose collection is also located in.
Arranged chronologically, the Correspondence, primarily from the years 1923 to 1932, consists of incoming letters pertaining to Klitgaard's artistic and literary ventures. Correspondents include artists and literary figures (Egmont Arens, Peggy Bacon, Virgil Barker, William Harlan Hale, Robert Preston Harriss, Ernest W. Harrold, Rockwell Kent, Alfred Kreymborg, William McFee, Harry Edward Maule, Henry Allen Moe, Hermon More, Ogden Nash, John Crowe Ransom, Henry Morton Robinson, Charles Allen Smart, Lowell Thomas); publishers (Doubleday, Doran and Company, Inc., William Edwin Rudge, Inc.); and art galleries (E. Weyhe). A selected index to the Correspondence follows the box list.
Artwork encompasses a lithographic plate, reproductions, sketchbooks, and sketches. The reproductions, with the exception of one exhibition catalog designed by Klitgaard, are all posters of maps (Greenwich Village, the Holy Land, Manhattan from the Battery to 59th Street) which may be found in Oversize Package #1. In addition to two Sketchbooks, there are three original pencil and watercolor sketches, as well as a number of photocopies.
Writings consists of a book dummy of Seven Months and Seven Days, an illustration proof for Through the American Landscape, an interview, a key to Klitgaard's map of the Holy Land, a photocopied review, a script, and published stories which are organized by title.
Memorabilia includes copyright certificates, personal photographs, poetry by Otto Gelsted, printed material, and reviews. Printed material contains newspaper clippings (1927-1946), two exhibition catalogs, and several literary periodical reviews (1941-1946). Holograph and typescript manuscripts by Daisy Sanial Gill, William McFee, Hughes Mearns, and Charles Allen Smart, as well as a radio script constitute Reviews.
Related Material
See also the
Egmont Arens Papers
,
Peggy Bacon Papers
,
Aaron Bohrod Papers
,
Georgina Klitgaard Papers
, and
Georgina Klitgaard Collection
.
Subject and Genre Headings
Art -- Painters; Arens, Egmont, 1889-1966.; Bacon, Peggy, 1895-1987.; Kent, Rockwell, 1882-1971.; Klitgaard, Kaj.; Kreymborg, Alfred, 1883-1966.; Maule, Harry E. (Harry Edward), 1886-; McFee, William, 1881-1966.; Nash, Ogden, 1902-1971.; Ransom, John Crowe, 1888-1974.; Robinson, Henry Morton, 1898-1961.; Roosevelt, Franklin D. (Franklin Delano), 1882-1945.; Smart, Charles Allen, 1904-1967.; Thomas, Lowell, 1892-1981.; Art, American.; Art, American -- 20th century.; Authors, American -- 20th century.; Danish Americans.; Novelists, American.; Painters -- United States.; Painting, American -- 20th century.; Articles.; Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Photographs.; Sketchbooks.; Sketches.; Artists.; Authors.; Novelists.; Painters.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Inventory
- Biographical material
  - Biographical material (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - Correspondence, 1914-1966; undated; 2 folders (Box 1)
    See Selected Index to Correspondence for notable names and dates.
- Artwork
  - Lithographic plate, 1936 (Box 1)
  - Reproductions
    - "The Circus in Paint", undated (Box 1)
    - Greenwich Village poster, undated (Oversize 1)
    - Holy Land poster, undated (Oversize 1)
    - Manhattan from the Battery to 59th Street poster, undated (Oversize 1)
  - Sketchbooks, "1940-1941,"; undated (Box 1)
  - Sketches
    - Pencil and watercolor (3), undated (Box 1)
    - Photocopies, undated (Box 1)
- Writings
  - Books
    - Seven Months and Seven Days, dummy (Box 1)
    - Through the American Landscape, illustration proof (Box 1)
  - Interviews
    - by Warren Bower, "Readers' Almanac", undated (Box 1)
  - Maps
    - Key to map of the Holy Land, 1927 (Box 1)
  - Reviews
    - Miscellaneous (photocopies), undated (Box 1)
  - Scripts
    - "The Art Dealer in Heaven," The Hue and Cry, 1929 (Box 1)
  - Stories
    - A-Z (by title), 1931; 1951,; undated (Box 1)
  - Miscellaneous
    - Photocopies of miscellaneous items, undated (Box 1)
- Memorabilia
  - Copyright certificates, 1927; 1929 (Box 1)
  - Photographs, 1925; 1939,; undated (Box 1)
  - Poetry by others - Gelsted, Otto, 1931 (Box 1)
  - Printed material
    - Clippings, 1927-1946; undated (Box 1)
    - Exhibition catalogs, 1929; undated (Box 1)
    - Reviews, 1941-1946; undated (Box 1)
  - Reviews
    - Holograph, typescript, 1929; 1930,; undated (Box 1)
    - Radio script - Higgins "Ship Ahoy" Program, WNOE, 1946 (Box 1)
  - Miscellany (Box 1)
Selected index to correspondence
The American Caravan 1929 Nov. 13
Arens, Egmont 1926 Mar. 12
Bacon, Peggy undated
Barker, Virgil undated
Carnegie Institute 1941 Apr. 24
Doubleday, Doran and Company, Inc. 1929 July 5 1929 Aug. 6 1929 Aug. 27 1929 Sept. 30 1929 Oct. 16 1929 Dec. 19 1930 Mar. 18 1930 Apr. 18 1930 May 9 1930 Aug. 6 1930 Sept. 3 1930 Dec. 8 1930 Dec. 15 1930 Dec. 29 1931 Feb. 10 undated
The Evening Citizen 1930 Feb. 19
The Evening Sun 1930 Apr. 26
[John Simon] Guggenheim Memorial Foundation 1953 Nov. 19
Hale, William Harlan undated
Harriss, Robert Preston 1930 Apr. 26
Harrold, Ernest W. 1930 Feb. 19
The Hue and Cry undated
Kent, Rockwell 1928 July 26 1928 Dec. 18 1929 Feb. 18 1929 Mar. 23 1929 Aug. 22 (Frances) 1930 Dec. 17 1936 Apr. 21
The Kenyon Review 1938 Oct. 1 1952 Nov. 18
Kreymborg, Alfred 1928 Mar. 16 1929 Nov. 13
The Literary Digest 1932 Feb. 19
McFee, William 1930 May 24 1930 June 8 1931 Oct. 14 undated
See also Reviews
Maule, Harry Edward 1929 Aug. 6 1929 Dec. 19 1930 May 9 1930 Dec. 15 1931 Feb. 10
Maverick Theater 1930 July 14
Moe, Henry Allen 1953 Nov. 19
More, Hermon undated
Nash, Ogden 1930 Mar. 18 1930 Apr. 18 1930 Aug. 6 1930 Sept. 3 1930 Dec. 8
New Masses 1926 Mar. 12
Ransom, John Crowe 1938 Oct. 1 1952 Nov. 18
Robinson, Henry Morton 1952 May 13
Roosevelt, Franklin D. 1936 Mar. 3
William Edwin Rudge, Inc. 1927 May 10 1927 Nov. 7 1928 Mar. 6 1928 Aug. 17 1930 June 19 1930 July 17 1931 Feb. 3
Smart, Charles Allen 1929 July 5 1929 July 26 1929 Aug. 27 1929 Sept. 30 1929 Oct. 13 undated
See also Reviews
Southern Pacific Company 1927 June 22 1928 Jan. 13
Thomas, Lowell 1932 Feb. 19
[E.] Weyhe 1927 June 16 1930 Feb. 21